Christoph Alt

RESEARCHER · SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Summary _____

I am a researcher / software engineer with 4+ years of experience (research and applied) in machine learning & natural language processing & distributed computing. Fluent in Python, Java, Python's scientific and machine learning stack, recent deep learning and natural language processing frameworks, Docker, and AWS. I am passionate about solving difficult problems with little data.

Experience _____



German Research Center for AI (DFKI)

Berlin

RESEARCHER AND PHD STUDENT

2017-(now)

- (Applied) research in **information extraction** with limited labeled data, explainability, and dialogue systems.
- I published and presented research at multiple top-tier conferences (e.g., ACL, EMNLP).
- I developed a dialogue system prototype that answers tens of millions of customer support requests per year.
- I developed an information extraction system that extracts thousands of supply-chain-related events (e.g., acquisitions) per day.



Zalando SE

Berlin

DATA SCIENTIST

2015-2017

- As part of the **query understanding and intent** team my goal was to improve customer search experience.
- I was partly responsible for architecture and system design during the transition towards a more intelligent search.
- I developed a query autocomplete and autosuggest system to assist customers with their search, which, by now, serves tens of millions of customers every month.



Technical University of Berlin

Berlin

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

2016-2017

- As a member of the Complex and Distributed IT Systems Group (CIT), I contributed to the design and development of "Exa", an experimental large scale **distributed machine learning** framework.
- I further implemented various distributed training strategies for commonly used machine learning algorithms.



Technical University of Berlin

Berlin

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

- As a member of the Database Systems and Information Management Group (DIMA), I contributed algorithms to the Apache Flink machine learning library and created content for the course "Scalable Data Mining, Concepts and Methods".
- I further developed a data processing pipeline to analyze large web corpora (e.g., Common Crawl) with Apache Spark and Flink.

Education _

Technical University of Berlin

Berlin

Dr.-Ing. in Computer Science, Machine Learning 2017–(Jan 2021)

- PhD thesis (defended): "Neural Sequential Transfer Learning for Relation Extraction", summa cum laude
- Supervisors: Prof. Sebastian Möller, Prof. Hans Uszkoreit
- I explored neural transfer learning for information extraction, specifically relation extraction from text (RE).
- · I improved upon state-of-the-art RE methods, and identified shortcomings of recent approaches and remaining challenges of the task.



Technical University of Berlin

Berlin

MSc in Computer Engineering

2014-2017

- Master thesis: "Adaptive Consistency Management for Distributed Machine Learning"
- Supervisors: Prof. Odej Kao, Prof. Volker Markl
- I explored different approaches to speed up distributed training of commonly used machine learning algorithms.
- · Courses on general machine learning, scalable data mining, natural language processing, and computer vision.



Munich University of Applied Sciences

Munich

BENG IN COMPUTER ENGINEERING

2009-2013

• Courses on embedded systems development, digital image processing, and network architectures.

Projects_

RelEx A comprehensive suite of baseline and state-of-the-art

neural relation extraction methods; based on AllenNLP.

REval A framework to develop and evaluate probing tasks, e.g., to diagnose linguistic features captured by neural relation extraction models; based on the SentEval toolkit.

Distributed hyperparameter search for AllenNLP; based on Ray. The core framework now powers AllenAI's allentune.

Skills ____

Programming Python (expert), Java (fluent), Rust (prior

experience), SQL

Libraries PyTorch, TensorFlow, JAX, numpy, scikit-learn,

pandas, AllenNLP, Spacy, StanfordNLP, etc.

Tools Docker, Elasticsearch, AWS, Apache Spark & Flink

& Hadoop & Kafka & Lucene & Solr

Languages German, English, French

Publications

- 12. **Christoph Alt**, Aleksandra Gabryszak and Leonhard Hennig, "TACRED Revisited: A Thorough Evaluation of the TACRED Relation Extraction Task", 58th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, 1558–1569, 2020. https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/2020.acl-main.142
- 11. **Christoph Alt**, Aleksandra Gabryszak and Leonhard Hennig, "Probing Linguistic Features of Sentence-level Representations in Neural Relation Extraction", 58th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, 1534–1545, 2020. https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/2020.acl-main.140
- David Harbecke and Christoph Alt, "Considering Likelihood in NLP Classification Explanations with Occlusion and Language Modeling", 58th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics: Student Research Workshop, 111–117, 2020. https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/2020.acl-srw.16
- 9. Hanchu Zhang, Leonhard Hennig, **Christoph Alt**, Changjian Hu, Yao Meng and Chao Wang, "Bootstrapping Named Entity Recognition in E-Commerce with Positive Unlabeled Learning", *The 3rd Workshop on e-Commerce and NLP*, 1–6, 2020. https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/2020.ecnlp-1.1
- 8. **Christoph Alt**, Marc Hübner and Leonhard Hennig, "Fine-tuning Pre-Trained Transformer Language Models to Distantly Supervised Relation Extraction", 57th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, 1388–1398, 2020. https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/P19-1134
- 7. **Christoph Alt***, Marc Hübner* and Leonhard Hennig, "Improving Relation Extraction by Pre-trained Language Representations", 2019 Conference on Automated Knowledge Base Construction, 1–18, 2019. https://openreview.net/forum?id=BJgrxbqp67
- 6. Robert Schwarzenberg, Marc Hübner, David Harbecke, **Christoph Alt** and Leonhard Hennig, "Layerwise Relevance Visualization in Convolutional Text Graph Classifiers", 13th Workshop on Graph-Based Methods for Natural Language Processing, 58–62, 2019. https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/D19-5308
- 5. Yang Li, Qingliang Miao, Ji Geng, **Christoph Alt**, Robert Schwarzenberg, Leonhard Hennig, Changjian Hu and Feiyu Xu, "Question answering for technical customer support", *International Conference on Natural Language Processing and Chinese Computing*, *Information*, 10, 63, 2018.
- 4. Guoguang Zhao, Jianyu Zhao, Yang Li, **Christoph Alt**, Robert Schwarzenberg, Leonhard Hennig, Stefan Schaffer, Sven Schmeier, Changjian Hu and Feiyu Xu, "MOLI: Smart Conversation Agent for Mobile Customer Service", *Information*, 10, 2, 2018.
- 3. David Harbecke, Robert Schwarzenberg and **Christoph Alt**, "Learning Explanations from Language Data", 2018 EMNLP Workshop BlackboxNLP: Analyzing and Interpreting Neural Networks for NLP, 316–318, 2018. https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/W18–5434
- 2. Roland Roller, **Christoph Alt**, Laura Seiffe and He Wang, "mEx An Information Extraction Platform for German Medical Text", 11th International Conference on Semantic Web Applications and Tools for Healthcare and Life Sciences
- 1. Tobias Herb, Tim Jungnickel and **Christoph Alt**, "Weak Consistency and Stochastic Environments: Harmonization of Replicated Machine Learning Models", 2nd Workshop on the Principles and Practice of Consistency for Distributed Data, 8, 3, 2016. https://doi.org/10.1145/2911151.2911161